so what are you gonna ask me tell me
butter Lu what I'm gonna ask is first to
describe what you how would you describe
the science of qualities that you
describe in the Masters yeah yeah yeah
start with that mm-hmm and we've only
got ten minutes like and then I was
hoping to ask you something about where
you see the place of ecovillages in the
move towards sustainability it's a
different project yeah and then about
how the Masters and ballistic signs came
about mm-hmm and hopefully they've got
time to ask something about good as well
yeah okay that's your fix
yeah um okay so could you describe what
you on the stand under the oath the
signs of qualities and how it differs
from conventional signs yeah
the science of quality is really an
extension of conventional science in the
sense that it depends upon consensus and
agreement and a methodology whereby
people come to recognize the the
agreement they have for the consensus
they have about the qualities of
experience of other beings and these are
the beings could be other animals they
can be landscapes they could be an
organization a room a building whatever
it may be and of course we live our
lives in terms of qualities more than
quantities quantities have become
important but it's the qualities that
really give the texture and the quality
to our lives and our relationships and
research relationship to become primary
in the new science
networks then we have to recover this
whole area of qualities and there are
systematic ways now of demonstrating
that the people reach consensus very
effectively about the qualities of
experience of form animals about the
quality that is expressed in a landscape
the quality of a river and so on these
these are things that people hold done
spontaneously at the common sense and
it's been excluded from science but now
we need to bring back in as a part of an
extension of science and quantities into
qualities and to what extent did the
work of yan was gone from good and play
into the science for qualities in the
early stage well constantly Gert is such
a wonderful example of a holistic
scientist and it's more than science and
they begin to eat he obviously was a
holistic human in a sense that he was
doing art and servants and he was using
the the approach of phenomenology to
observe the qualities of beings as well
as their quantities he put the two
together and the systematic way of
exploring the natural world I want to
say natural world I mean everything are
not distinct for me big distinguishing
between nature and culture and so that's
the unification that's being achieved
and Gerta is a wonderful example of how
you can how you can do that
systematically and integrate all the
different ways of knowing the intuitive
the sensory the feeling and the
analytical
so the thinking and you put all those
together and you've got you've got an
integrated way of knowing the world and
acting in it considerably and how did
the idea of setting up the Masters of
holistic science come about and and tell
a little bit about the story what oh you
actually and set it up yeah yes
I had always ever since my experiences
at the University of Sussex in the 60s
and 70s when you had that a kind of a
period of enlightenment I mean the 60s
phenomena was pretty remarkable and at
Sussex it was really very well developed
and so it it gave me a sense that we
need to do some stat abolish the
boundaries between traditional subjects
but not lose any of the rigour
now that sounds contradictory but you
can be very rigorous in your your your
thinking and your analysis well at the
same time you are encompassing the whole
range of these different ways of knowing
now that's a bit of a challenge and it's
something I didn't know what the
solution was to it and I still don't but
I was exploring that at the University
of Sussex and then at the Open
University but there are boundaries to
academic permission and so when I came
to Schumacher in nineteen in 1996 I was
really rather astonished to realize that
it was possible to explore this
territory of holistic science
systematically grounding it in chaos
complexity and Gaia theories and
incorporating all these different
and of course with Stefan Hani together
we reconstructed this program who was
accepted by Plymouth and the the bits
that have been not adequately developed
and are still being developed or the
areas of experiential learning and
practical engagement with the land and
with buildings and this implementation
of the principles of holistic science in
holistic living so that's where that's
where the Masters has been going for the
last four years five years but it's been
a slow development and now I think this
need for a real push in that direction
yes we're getting so do you see that
there's a and when you say holistic
living that Lynn's very strongly into
the current climate change response and
the need for increased sustainability
yeah what are the movements where you
see like is permaculture the Eco village
movement possibly part of a more
holistic way of living in the earth and
how do you see these grassroots
movements contribute it's absolutely
central I mean what we are now doing at
the college is is turning what we call
long culture this monoculture of lawns
into permaculture agroforestry
following Martin Crawford's inspiration
and other people in the open bill
Mollison elicits this whole vision of
having something beautiful natural
productive low-maintenance and so that
is the direction in which the colleges
moving and we want to move the whole
estate and of course with transition
town Totnes we want to have a
cooperative engagement in this whole
process of putting into operation as a
Nubble holistic community
and have an example here in the
southwest of how this is this is going
to be achieved and that is beginning to
move in the direction of implementation
in a way that I think is very exciting
we don't know we know the direction in
which we're going we don't know what the
outcomes going to be nobody does and we
don't know how long it's going to take
but we know what we have to do and we're
sort of getting on with it and this
whole idea of steering into the future
without knowing necessarily where you're
going and is somehow informed by some of
the insights that you gained through a
long engagement will complexity theory
could you say a little bit more about
them the lessons that complexity the
theory and experiences of the Santa Fe
Institute and your country yeah but
complexity theory that was they it can
essentially it opened a scientific
window onto this way of knowing the
world because it said look we cannot we
can't predict what happens in complex
systems they're just that there's too
rich a set of interactions and so what
we have to do is work with complex
systems feel them use your intuition and
your feelings to to get a sense of how
things are moving and to move them in
the right direction this has to be done
consensus early in the group but at the
same time this connects regattas
approach which is the quantities
qualities and the artistic as well as
the scientific
the devotee so it's art science craft
technology business commerce everything
is now joined together and these
communities eco village communities or
whatever you want to call them these new
communities for holistic living are
embodying these integrated principles
now complexity was the root we use to
convince the University of Plymouth that
that this was a legitimate and valid and
scientific scientific a well grounded
way of proceeding but he's gone for
beyond that though and in some sense
common sense validates this but backed
up by again rigorous observation we're
doing research in this area and so
things are moving in a way that I think
combine the the elements of intuition
thinking feeling sensing I mentioned
before the Union mandala is becoming a
unity in these holistic patterns of
living lifestyles and from my experience
of doing them of the Masters one of the
big lessons that that came out of
complexity theory and chaos theory was
the switch from a mindset of prediction
and control to one of participation and
the realization that complex systems the
the big complex system in which we're
taking part is fundamentally
unpredictable and uncontrollable could
you connect yes that's the whole idea
you know living on the edge of chaos or
experiencing the world coming into being
it's actually a give us that there's a
Gerty ignore and abort off the flux is
locked and it's this idea that
everything is always coming into being
and we need to experience the world as
process now given that this is
fundamental we cannot predict what the
outcomes going to be
but we can feel the direction in which
this is moving and it's that sense of
engagement and participation and a deep
involvement in present not concern about
the future but actually being very
sensitive to all the elements that are
working now and that's what I think is
the process of mm-hmm
you know living in the eternal present
because we cannot predict the future and
so the the more present you are the the
better will be your antenna for working
out what the right directions so it's
the journey it's not the goal it's the
journey this is perennial wisdom is
classical it's in Buddhism it's in
Christianity if you look at the
fundamentals of it it's in any religion
using indigenous cultures
this is perennial wisdom this what we're
getting back to I think or getting on to
and embodying that together with all the
technology and know-how and the
analytical knowledge that we have their
disposal